Hello everybody welcome it is September
26th
2023 we are here kicking off a new
stream series at the Active inference
Institute this is the morph stream
1.1 today we have David kapple and also
this section and streams facilitated by
Sarah Hamburg we're going to have a
overview first presented by Sarah then
David will share some work on
neuromorphic Computing and then we'll
have some time to discuss so thank you
both for joining and Sarah to you for
the first presentation and also to
introduce yourself if you'd like yes
that's a good idea thank you very much
Daniel um so my name is Sarah um I'm a
neuroscientist specializing intelligence
currently working in the field of
neuromorphic computing um at chef field
Hal in the UK so I'm going to give you a
high level overview of what neuromorphic
Computing is and before we hear David's
exciting talk in the first edition of
this new series um just to let you know
if you're watching on double time in the
future I talk quite fast so you might
not want to watch me on double time so
this QR code um I put here will take you
to a paper which I thought was a really
nice introduction to the field um but
neic Computing can be defined as
Computing systems that are designed to
mimic the structure and function of the
nervous system so this doesn't have to
be the human nervous system the field
actually takes inspiration from all
sorts of animals and insects um although
the definitions online don't necessarily
acknowledge that so some people are
quite open with what constitutes
neuromorphic while maybe others would
prefer neuromorphic was reserved for
Hardware instantiations of biological
like neurons um which are sometimes
referred to as non-run computers and I
think that's what the paper that the QR
code um will refers to it as in as their
definition um so what I think is really
interesting is a little bit of the
context so like our current vuman
computer architecture was also inspired
by Neuroscience and particularly the
Mull and pits 43 Neuron model um
inspired Von y's first draft in 1945 so
Neuroscience has a long history of um
inspiring computer science and this also
includes reinforcement learning which is
based on theories about learning
decision- making from behavioral
psychology based on rewards and
punishments and also heian learning
principles of cells that fire together
wire together um from 49 became
foundational for unsupervised learning
so first of all um hang on one
second so um in order to understand the
why of neuromorphic computing I really
wanted to explain what's so great about
the brain so uh here's some inspiration
for light bulbs so I'm going to ask you
a question I just want you to think
about it for a second in terms of light
bulbs how much energy do you think the
brain uses do you think it's more or
less energy than the bulbs lighting the
room that you're in if you're in the
future by all means PA this pause this
if if you want to do some in-depth
calculations but I'm going to skip to
the answer the answer is here in the
pink circle so it's 20 watts so that's
the equivalent of one modern day energy
efficient light bulb so that's probably
what's above me now basically in my room
here um this QR code should take you to
quite an interesting paper on power
consumption in the brain if you're
interested in
that so that works out about four
Bananas a Day to power your brain and
this is calculated by the way based on a
calorie intake that the brain needs so
for context the fastest supercomputer in
Europe I think it's called Lumi in
Finland um it's been called
exceptionally green and its power
consumption is 8.5 million Watts so
that's around half a million light bulbs
well your brain uses just one so then
the question is well what does your
brain do with that one light bulb or
four
bananas apparently it does 1,000 billion
calculations per second so so there's
lots of other massive estimates out
there uh this wasn't even the largest by
several orders of magnitude estimates
are obviously very speculative um but
they're all massive and they all tend to
be based on the number of neurons their
connections and firing rates um but I
think it's really important for the
context that supercomputers can't
actually yet match you know our
complexity of skills um or the
adaptability of the human brain so we
actually Excel Way Beyond supercomputers
when it comes to things like complex
decision- making uh learning from
experience
so how does your brain compare to AI um
so I mentioned that modern AI is already
brain inspired however artificial
neurons are highly simplified they don't
they don't capture the complexity of
biological neurons or networks like not
even close um individual neurons are
actually more like networks themselves
and research suggests that modeling one
biological neuron requires a five to
eight layer di deep artificial neuron
Network made of around a thousand
artificial neurons this QR code should
take you to the paper for
that you have 86 billion neurons in your
brain uh they work together to form a
highly energy efficient low latency
supercomputer that works just above room
temperature of the equivalent of about
four Bananas a Day so hopefully I've
given you a sense of how amazing your
brain is um as if you didn't know that
already and how it's already been used
to inspire the I guess fairly basic AI
that we have now compared to human
intelligence so next I'm going to
explain how key features of the brain
are being implemented to catalyze our
next generation of AI and Technology
through the field of neuromorphic
computing which is why you're all here
so traditional vum and computers have
physically separate Computing and memory
units shown here on the left uh during
computation data must transfer backwards
and forwards like really fast so there's
a bottleneck essentially for Speed and
energy um whereas in neuromorphic
architectures which are shown here on
the right with the help of Dary
Computing and memory occur in the same
place so they're said to be
collocated essentially individual
neurons perform computation while
memories represented by the strength of
the connections the weights between
neurons so the copses so chips like this
might be created with components uh like
mistas for example which can emulate
synaptic weights and this architecture
improves speed it reduces energy
consumption and what's really
interesting is it enables massively
parallel processing meaning that
multiple problems can be worked on at
the same time so this is particularly
important this architecture for various
use cases but also because as we reach
the end of Moos log which is the number
of transistors you able to physically
make tinier and tinier to fit on a chip
and it's also important because Humanity
needs to massively reduce its energy
consumption against the backdrop drop of
creating ever more powerful
AI so artificial neurons uh typically
use continuous activation shown on the
left they're always on while
neuromorphic neurons they're said to be
spiking so they're on or they're off
which is shown here on the right so
similar to sort of an action potential
so the benefits for this are again power
efficiency um and also applications
where timing is important and this is
given that their event driven so
essentially they have um the potential
for spatial and temporal Dimensions
which then enables added spatio temporal
encoding and processing of information
uh you might be wondering bit about gpus
um which also enable parallel processing
uh research suggests that gpus are
suitable architectures for deploying
spiking your networks um which I think
makes this a really interesting time for
the field given how highend gpus are
becoming ever more
pervasive um so the brain learn strength
of synapsis between neurons this is
based on pre and post synaptic firing
patterns I think David's talk will talk
a lot we'll go into a lot more depth on
this but there are many different typ
types and patterns of this across the
brain depending on the types of synapses
such as excitatory to inhibitory
excitatory to
excitatory um and the neurom market
field is working to leverage these rules
um because of benefits for on chip
learning and also applications such as
pattern recognition and Edge Computing
as well Edge Computing being quite a
huge use case for neuromorphic computing
because of the sort of event driven
nature and also the low energy usage and
this QR code should take you to quite an
interesting paper um on stdp that I
found so what neuromorphic Solutions are
available now you might just think it's
s theoretical uh there are actually many
different solutions out there which I'll
just give you a really high level
overview of so the human brain project
has created several large scale
neuromorphic computers including spica
which is this one at the bottom this
boards like maybe like I don't know the
size of my face or something so that
runs in real time um and it's comprised
of multiple general purpose on
microprocessors and there was also brain
scales which is an accelerated analog
architecture and it runs a thousand
times real time so the um the board next
to the blue one that's an actual credit
card size um version of brain scales
which they've recently made which I
thought was pretty cool um and then
there's also some big players in the
space so this blue one here is Intel's
Loi chip they're on to lii 2 now that's
their neuromorphic chip and they have an
open source software framework for that
as well because they really want to
catalyze the open source key Community
to get involved with it so neuromorphic
sensors also exist so this little blue
thing in the middle is actually a
neuromorphic camera it's maybe like this
big um so they aim to recreate how our
nervous system senses stimulate such as
light so for example in a neuromorphic
camera which is the one here each pixel
works independently with a microsc
resolution hopefully my GIF will work oh
there we go so you can see each pixel
working there which is pretty cool so
compared to traditional digital cameras
they have improved performance with
motion and lower power consumption there
was also a neuromorphic nose recently by
Intel which was pretty cool um so it
could learn the scent of a chemical
after just one exposure um and then it
could identify that scent even when it
was masked by others and then finally
this is a humanoid robot called an iub
and what you can do is you can actually
integrate neuromorphic sensors such as
the camera and then neuromorphic chips
maybe spa or brain scales into a
humanoid device like this or other
devices like a drone and then from that
you can actually create embodied
neuromorphic systems uh and this is
something that we work on at the Smart
interactive Technologies research lab in
Sheffield in the
UK this slide just highlights some of
the potential applications of
neuromorphic computing which I thought
were quite interesting when you think
about it so the understanding of context
pattern recognition Advanced sensing few
shot learning generalizing across tasks
complex decision- making explainability
and brain interfaces um so all these
skills are really beneficial when you're
thinking about human- centered realtime
applications in Dynamic environments so
things like self-driving cars for
example and personally I think that
neuromorphic systems um are also likely
to be the future substrate of brain
computer interfaces probably a bit
biased because I'm a neuroscientist but
um they're low energy they're real time
and they also have architectures which
match our own Hardware so I do think
we'll soon see the BCI field being
catalyzed by neuromorphic systems
particular
maybe for hybrids of hardware and and
wetwear so maybe even potentially
containing people's own um you know
brain cells which you can actually grow
just from a hair
cell and the particular focus of our
work is designing AI which learns in a
similar way to a human so it has an
innate sense of curiosity and it learns
through interacting with the real world
so in the 50s Alan Turing said instead
of trying to produce a program to
simulate the adult mind why not rather
try to produce one which stimulates the
child's brain If This Were then subject
to an appropriate course of Education
one would obtain the adult brain this is
very much the philosophy behind the
neurodevelopmental approach um to Ai and
neuromorphic Computing which I just
wanted to
highlight um there are some challenges
in the field these are very high level
but I'll just give you a little bit of
an idea of it so training spiking neural
networks is more complex than
traditional neural networks also
designing Hardware which actually
implement spiking neural networks stdp
on a large scale is said to be fairly
challenging and then also developing
algorithms which can actually
effectively leverage all these like
Technologies so the hardware the stdp
it's an ongoing active area of
research um so if you're here you're
probably interested in active inference
so I wanted to highlight this actually
someone put on the Discord today one of
these studies which is pretty cool so a
couple of recent Studies have um
combined neuromorphic Computing with
principles of active inference so active
inference comes from neuroscience and I
would argue that it lends itself very
well to neuromorphic
architectures um in a recent paper on
embodied neuromorphic intelligence so
not not it didn't really mention active
inference in it the QR code on the top
right here um it was suggested that a
real breakthrough in neuromorphics will
happen if the whole system design is
based on biological computational
principles with a tight into playay
between the estimation of the
surroundings and the robot's own State
and decisionmaking planning and action
so some of those themes might sound
quite familiar to people interested in
active inference and U I would suggest
that active inference is well placed to
meet these requirements and I just
wanted to highlight a couple of recent
studies here so this one on the left
gandal FAL recently demonstrated
plasticity and Rapid unsupervised
learning in a neuromorphic system using
active inference principles the author
suggested that their experiments could
be adopted to implement brain-like
predictive capabilities in neuro neuro
morphic robotic systems and then there
was the dish frin paper which some of
you may be familiar with by Kagan atal
so this was a hybrid um wetwear Hardware
neuromorphic system that the author's
claimed was embodied the system showed
rapid parent learning of the game of
pong using the free energy principle for
Learning and the authors claimed that
the system exhibited synthetic
biological
intelligence so the field implementing
active influence principles in
neuromorphic systems is very nent and
the idea behind this mream series is to
create a space and a community to share
knowledge ideas and expertise to
catalyze the field um I think some
really exciting technological leaps are
probably going to come from this area so
thank you for listening to my uh quick
run through neuromorphic 101 um and next
up we're gonna hear from David so David
over to you if you want to introduce
yourself please thank you
Sarah um I would
share my
screen
[Music]
yeah can you see now
my screen the presentation yeah okay
perfect okay yeah hello my my name is
David kle I'm a researcher and coup
leader at The Institute for um M
informatic at the University of bom um
so I'm uh leading the group on
sustainable machine learning and we have
a very strong focus on neuromorphic
Computing that's why I'm here
today and I'm going to start with a very
similar motivation than Sarah did which
was really a great um inspiration for
this talk I think um so probably most of
you have seen this um this interesting
recent result and I don't mean Germany
winning the basketball championship ship
but um this really big leap in uh in
artificial intelligence that we have
seen in the last years especially the
last two or three years so this is a
picture generated from a prompt by a
doly network and it's it's really
amazing and was considered science
fiction like only two three years
ago and this was essentially made uh
possible by a neuromorphic approach
which is deep neural networks and this
these uh deep neural networks have
become huge now but this comes also with
a caveat so basically the flip side is
that this um among other problems maybe
these models may have they consume uh
huge amounts of energy so models like um
Dal or jet GPT they as Sarah already
mentioned they they would consume um
energy budgets that are comparable to
houses or cars so training um jgpt a
single time is like a giga hour
approximately so that would be 300 tons
of CO2 emission um and many times the
which comes down to many times the life
uh span of a of a typical car so this
comes with two problems obviously uh
this makes training these models only
accessible to a very small number of
very large players so essentially the
big tech companies and secondly and
maybe even more importantly this is not
compatible with uh planet with uh
limited resources so if the growth rate
of AI continues like it did in the last
years it will
consume uh 133% of the global energy
consumption by 20 30 and it will
basically outrun um the transportation
sector in in another five years or
so so this raises the question does
sustainable machine learning exist at
all and obviously since I'm working in
the group of sustainable machine
learning I believe it does
and why I think it does is because we
know a system that um is very efficient
and is still probably better than these
these AI models which is the human brain
which consumes as Sarah mentioned around
watts uh or four Bananas a
Day uh and uh so it's it's many orders
of magnitude more efficient than the AI
models we have
today uh but so far we don't know
essentially how these networks work um
and especially how to train them and
basically our our goal is to transfer
now mechanisms from machine learning
that's so you have this nice picture
here uh basically we start from the
machine learning site where we already
know our way around um so we have these
models that are wonderful and that are
quite that that give us really
impressive results but they are not
efficient and we want to trans transfer
them to um new efficient uh AI
generation and our ideas is to use
inspiration from Neuroscience um that
make this transfer faster and and
possible in the first
place okay so and actually biology is a
great source of inspiration and always
comes around the corner with very
surprising results and one of these
results that I stumbled Upon A couple of
years ago is that the the ability of um
copses in the brain so as you probably
know neurons in your brain are connected
for
copses um but if you look at the so so
this is a paper from
2019 and they could actually identify
individual Sy upses and they could
trigger them to uh make a synoptic
release like a single transmission but
if you look at this um um at these
measurements you see that this is really
covered in and noise so essentially if
you basically average over this and zoom
this out you see here these typical
synoptic traces which is the average
white line here but below that you see
this huge chitter so there's they really
like go several um standard deviations
up and
down um and this is actually very
surprising given that uh neurons are
probably the single most costly cell
type in your body in terms of energy
consumption they really in or in
comparison they they they consume quite
a bit of energy in your body so you
would expect that these transitions or
Transmissions that are communicated
between neurons which are very costly uh
should be highly reliable so this is
very counterintuitive this results and
has been puzzling neuroscientists for
quite a while
now um and then there is
a there is a second um puzzling observ
obervation which is
uh that the morphology of neurons looks
some somewhat like this so this would be
a typical pyramidal neuron you have in
your
cortex um but you see that this is
actually for a cell quite quite big and
elongated so this is this can be up to a
millimeter in in the human brain uh
which means that if a signups fires
somewhere here uh it has a very hard
time communicating with the cell body
which is down here so electrical signals
that are produced here uh May travel
down here but the the signups up here
has no way of measuring uh the actual
voltages at the cell body and this is
actually the interesting place because
here are the action potentials formed so
if the the signups would really like to
know about what is going on in the cell
body so that it can make predictions
about how the uh neuron will behave and
how it interacts with the world and this
is another very puzzling um um or open
problem in in Neuroscience how this
communication actually works out in in
single neurons between the cell body and
the uh and the signups it is known that
actually the action potentials can
travel back up so they see kind of this
binary variable when the uh when the
neuron spikes but they cannot actually
measure the membrane potential down here
so only the most prominent electric
signals can actually back propagate
through this
uh and this this suggests that the
signups actually has very sparse
information about what's going on with
this um uh in the cell body and uh most
models of synoptic plasticity don't
cover this at
all so and we were wondering um how do
this uh how does this interaction work
how can the
um uh signups produce useful learning
signals given this sparse information
about this important state of the of the
neuron and our idea was that essentially
these two observations these high levels
of noise and the signups and this um
large distance between cell body and and
signups say which give these high
uncertainties these are actually the two
sides of the same coin so our hypothesis
was that um actually we could use the
same models um that we know already from
from the behavioral level uh how an
agent can in uh can act and perform in
an environment of high uncertainty and
we just apply this
to um uh to every signups and oh there's
an error so every signups should utilize
this um these same models
basically and uh this model would
immediately suggest that actually
synoptic Trans Transmissions should be
noisy and these levels of noise would
Express uncertainty about the
environment and then we can use this
model to derive um learning rules and we
can compare them side by side to
biology and this is the first thing I
want to show you so um I just give a
very quick introduction to the free
energy model uh because some some of you
might not be that familiar with it but
this is essentially um a model to
describe a situation like this you have
a person that is interacting with some
environment and here I assumed very
simple so this person tries to um ball
to some Target and we as humans we are
we are good in solving such tasks and we
are also good in solving such tasks if
there is high levels of uncertainty in
this so if the person may receive the
some visual feedback but a lot of this
feedback may be hidden so I you can
imagine this going on behind some
wall and the person now still might want
to predict what is the trajectory of
this ball flying towards the target so
that it can make an correct uh action so
we will assign some variables to this uh
these states here so we have essentially
this feedback that this person can
observe and we have this unobserved
state of the ball flying here which we
call U where the person doesn't have
direct access to it would only see parts
of it for example when the ball is at
the corners of the wall appearing and
then uh to to model this essentially or
to to describe this uh Behavior the the
person would uh have an internal
description of this trajectory so an
internal model of this um State
U uh and the model this model would then
be updated to match the observed
feedback and this can be described very
nicely in this beautiful mathematical
framework of the free enery principle so
the idea is that you would essentially
um establish a model of your internal
States so essentially how the um
internal States and the uh state of the
environment
interact and you would have a model of
the feedback so how the states and the
feedback You observe interact and
essentially you can then write down um a
loss function that uh that measures the
distance between this model of the
internal State and this model of the
feedback and the uh external state
um
and uh then by essentially minimizing
this distance between the two you can
derive all sorts of behavior relevant
um can solve behaviorally relevant
problems for example learning but you
can also use this for other things like
uh figuring out what are good actions
for example so making inference about
both the internal States and the actions
for example and this is shell the free
energy principle and this object here
happens to be what is known as the
variational free energy which is also
just coincides with statistical physics
and this is where this framework has its
name from but you see that it's a all is
probabilistic here so essentially you
have two probability functions Q for the
internal model and P for this
interaction between uh States and
observations and you have here uh a
distance measure between them that you
want to
minimize so now if we look at the neuron
and the signups and how they interact
with each other we find a very similar
picture so single signups um which we
have here in green has um an inter
internal state which we for Simplicity
model only uh as the synoptic bait based
on this the signups when it's triggered
by a preoptic spike it would generate um
a post synoptic current this would then
propagate to the Som which is our uh
external state which we can cannot
directly observe because it's too far
away from the cups but we can see a
feedback which is this spe propagating
action potential which is this binary
variable that tells us whether the
neuron has spiked or not so this is
exactly the same framework if you if we
write it down like that and we can just
use the same mathematics to solve it um
so to to solve it we only have to come
up with a couple of of um we have to
make a couple of assumptions so we have
to uh write down a model for this guy
here so this uh model of how the uh
feedback and the and the external State
interact uh but we have very good models
for this this has been studied over many
years so here you see how typically a
model neuron behaves so you have here um
the membrane potential of a leaky
integrated fire neuron and you see that
this is just uh going up and down so
this neuron would receive uh a lot of
preoptic input and maybe also noise and
eventually at some point it hits a
threshold it would generate a spike so
that would be the Z that travels to the
downstream neurons and also back to the
cups uh and then it
resets uh right um but now this's uh so
we can write this down mathematically is
a very simple um differential equation
but the uh neuron doesn't have access to
this state again so it's again behind
this wall it only sees this Spike events
but we can actually for this simple case
of really integrated F neuron we can
solve this analytically so we can write
down what is the posterior distribution
of membrane potentials given the spike
times and what uh comes out of this is
actually a so-called um stochastic
Bridge model or in this case of a uh of
a leak integr in fire neuron it's an
orang Bridge model so this can be
written down analytically and this U I
mean it's not simple but it's it's
doable uh and we can then just use this
directly so this model that we have uh
to again write down this uh free energy
functional so we make here an assumption
how the signups actually produces post
synoptic currents and how they're
integrated in the in the neuron but
that's also given by The Leaky
integrated fire neuron and actually the
stochastic um inputs that the signups
generates so in this for Simplicity we
only assume here basically gausian Sy
upses that would inject draw a gausian
random variable and inject this to inte
great and fire neuron and then all these
ingredients actually can be solved in
closed form and we can derive learning
rules that would minimize this pre
energy functional
now uh and if we do that
um uh this has a bunch of nice
properties because this Onin lbeck
bridge is completely determined by the
preent uh by the back propagating Action
potentials so basically the times of the
post synoptic um spikes that arrive at
the
[Music]
neuron um this shape that we get here
only depends on two neighboring
postoptic
spikes um which means that we get here
automatically uh a learning rule that
looks like this so learning rule that
only depends on the difference between
two postoptic spikes which we call here
Delta
T2 um and uh the difference between the
post synoptic Spike and the actual input
that is triggered at some point uh on
the preoptic
side uh and we can basically make here
this lookup table and just uh just
compute what would be the update that
these signups would need to make so that
it learns optimally in terms of this
free energy principle and this is the
shape that we get out you see that there
is a strong dependence on the post
synoptic firing rate but there's also a
dependence on basically this typical STP
that Sarah mentioned before uh what is
the relative positioning of of the pre
and postoptic
Spike so in a nutshell this model can
now be split into essentially two
Pathways so we have this atoc response
which basically just whenever there is a
preoptic spike that triggers an action
in the cups he would draw from this
scussion distribution and inject it into
the um into the neuron and then there is
this postt
talk uh update where we where the
signups would look up um in this orang
and wenck Bridge what would have been
the optimal um output that it should
have generated so what would have been
the optimal action and then it compares
the actual action with this optimal
action according to this free energy
principle and then generates a delayed
response response which is an update of
the synoptic
weight okay and importantly this uh
internal model is only implicit it's
encoded so to say into this um uh Spike
time dependent plasticity
rule uh so how do these rules then look
and do they compare to how do they
compare to biology and uh actually they
the fit is quite nicely given that this
is derived really from first principles
without making any assumptions so this
is the measurement in biology this is
this um B at Al rule B and po very old
work where they actually did this in uh
in vro studies where they measured the
injected pre and post synoptic um spikes
and then they measured what is the
weight change in the cops and this is
the rule that is predicted by our uh
model and you see that it at least in a
first order approximation it gives us
very similar shapes and this also makes
sense because
um the the signups wants to um change
the most when it's close to a uh close
to the pre and postoptic Spike times
because this is where or or the
postoptic spike times because this is
where it knows the most about the state
of the PO neuron the free energy
principle would actually suggest uh this
kind of cones
U um with almost no assumption
essentially but uh we also get because
we have a not just the first order uh
Spike time dependent plasticity rule but
uh we also have this dependency on the
postop firing rate we can also compare
this to other results and this here is
this old by gr and Brunel so this is
actually a model but that was very
detailed um describing the um the uh
plasticity based on the pre and
postoptic firing rate in uh in a signups
and this is what our model predicts so
if we inject random pre and post
synoptic popik tra uh trains with
different rates our model would predict
this shape which again is not a perfect
match but given that this is a u very
idealistic model it's actually least the
the main features that uh low firing
rates on the postoptic side would lead
to depression and higher to potentiation
um are reflected in
this okay uh I I assume I still have 10
minutes right okay so I would um give a
quick intermediate summary and then I
want to show some other work where we
actually apply this now to um to actual
machine learning
model um so what we have seen here is
that um Sy upses are actually um are
very stochastic and it was a very this
was a big puzzle and we suggests that
actually the
um uh that the the synaptic noise is
actually the signups is way of um
reporting its own uncertainty about the
environment where the environment is
actually the um the POS synoptic neuron
and it really interacts in this fashion
of the free energy principle with this
post synoptic neuron or that's a very
nice way of describing it and uh if
you're interested more there's a a paper
a pre-print out you can read up on all
this okay um so how does this now
connect to neuromorphics and actually so
we are not actually doing neuromorphic
Hardware we are doing doing neuromorphic
algorithms so we try to to bring these
Inspirations now into actual machine
learning models and we thought that this
might be a good um attack angle to um
solve a problem that is well known in
machine learning so I I just um uh yeah
Drew here a very simple um convolutional
neur networks with various convolutional
layers and then maybe some dense layers
that you would have in your machine
learning algorithm and the way this is
trained as many of you know I guess is
through um end to endend and arrowback
propagation so the idea is that you have
a training set which has inputs and uh
targets so for example in a
classification task this could be uh
pictures of cats and dogs and you would
have targets which are U class labels so
to say so some there's there's actually
artificial neurons in there and some one
of these neuron may be active for cats
and one may be active for
dogs um and in your training that data
you have exactly these labels um that
were generated by human that were
sitting down doing this by hand and then
during training you show this examples
to the network by propagating this
inputs uh all the way from the input
layer to the output layer then the
output is here compared to the uh to
these hand label targets and then the
mismatch between the two is back
propagated through all these layers back
to the input and all the weights or the
synoptic weights that are here uh in
between uh inside this layer
would then be updated accordingly so
that after doing this many many times uh
this network becomes good in telling a
part C
dos so this has a problem this this
algorithm it works great in practice and
it's it's the foundation of all these
models we have talked about like D or J
gbt but it is quite inefficient and the
problem is this what is known in the
literature as the Locking problem so if
you would split up this network now into
blocks which I already did before but
this is arbitrary but for for
implementing this efficiently in terms
of a software algorithm it might be
interesting to do that and now you would
want these blocks ideally to to run in
parallel so that you can basically uh
show the first example and uh on this
first block and then already train it
while the second um block is doing
something else but this is not really
possible with um end to end back
propagation because of this locking
problem because the activ ation of the
second block depends on the activation
of the first block so you have to
propagate it all the way to the end then
you compute this error and you would
then back propagate and only when this
is done uh you can start the next Epoch
where you show a new bunch of um of
examples uh and you see that during all
this time here the the threet that would
run this first block maybe uh would be
idle and has to wait essentially all the
time and this obviously makes them very
inefficient and now I our idea was that
we use basically uh what we had learned
from this earlier model on um on how
sign upses communicate over these long
distances for this free energy principle
and also apply it just to a deep neuron
Network and the ideas that you have here
again this basically you have already
this
um this generation of inputs to some
output but what what is missing to make
it applicable to the free energy
principle is this feedback that you
always need the idea was that we put
here very lightweight um uh feedback
Network so essentially each of these
blocks now in this deep neural network
would uh be accompanied by a feedback
block uh that locally generates a Target
so we used to really in the simplest
case which we have so this is very
recent work we only used linear blocks
so far so these are single linear layers
and we would generate now these these
outputs here in these feedback blocks
and then use the free energy principle
to derve um uh a local loss that allows
us again to minimize both these uh
feedback weights that we have here and
also the weights in the forward
Network um so it's essentially the same
idea so we have here these outputs which
we interpret now as a parameters to a
probability function so we can apply
this probabilistic framework
uh but now the all the rest basically
rolls out the same way so we uh assume
that these outputs are essentially um
the internal states of this model and we
have this um uh this observations given
in the uh inputs and and the targets and
now we try to minimize basically uh P
would now be this feed forward Network
and Q would be now a function that uh
contains um features of both the
feedback and the uh and the feed forward
Network and the nice thing is that if we
um uh I don't have time to go into to
the details now but if you write this
out you see that um this actually uh
decomposes this lock term here
decomposes into local linear terms that
give you these local losses here so
essentially that you can minimize here
block local between B and the
corresponding feedback block um a loss
function and you can then actually do
this in parallel so because uh maybe the
picture is good to see here so what you
have to do now you have a bit of
overhead because you have this feedback
block so this would be the two uh uh
execution times of the uh feed forward
block and the feedback
block but in principle they can run in
parallel uh and once the forward block
is done the next forward block can start
propagating through this
network um but simultaneously already
the forward block because it already
received a Target here can start uh
updating the weights and when it's done
it's free to operate on the next Epoch
so there is no locking anymore in this
in this
framework okay so I'm pretty much done
I'm also out of time I think so how does
this perform of course we changed the
the learning algorithm now we have to
also go back and see if this is uh
still uh giving us the same performance
and actually for um so this as I said is
this is the first um results we have
here now and at least to um midscale uh
data sets like Cypher 10 or so this
seems to actually uh perform very well
so we are tried it for for standard
architectures fashion mnist with reset
15 and res 18 we worked mostly so far uh
for like small data sets like fashion
amist we we've applying free splits to
reset 50 we get basically the same
performance as standard backrop as
networks get deeper uh you see that
there's actually um the our problem that
we have now is actually overfitting
because we have these local targets it
seems that these smaller blocks actually
overfit to some extent this is not so
severe for still up to tasks like Cypher
t so we get quite close already but if
you go now for really large tasks um
there's still something missing we are
uh for for like single splits we're
getting there but we're not reaching all
the way up to back propagation but it's
still interesting to see that you can
apply this um this principle also uh to
this standard machine learning
algorithms okay this is my second
summary so actually we found that um
deep Nur networks are surprisingly good
in generalizing over probability spaces
this is how actually this work
started um and we we our idea was to
exploit this um and to utilize it for to
distribute learning in the in the same
fashion as um in the first project I
showed you um and to solve this credit
assignment Problem by generating these
feedback
networks um yeah that's basically it and
then um I want to acknowledge my my
co-workers and my students so I have two
very good um um PhD students KH and
cabel who is now here in in bom and
works um on this topic and I the first
um project I showed was B I did together
when I was in gutan with Christian TL
and uh this project the second project
is I work I worked closely with
Christian mea and Anan
supron
and yeah thank
you thank you very much David that was
absolutely fascinating I think it's
incredible how closely the sort of model
matched biology like considering you
derived it from first principles I think
that was really cool um I did have a
question just about the the last sort of
the bit you spoke about the
convolutional network and you know you
said traditionally has to go all the way
end to end which is really inefficient
and then you showed the results that you
got did you look at energy consumption
with with yours as well uh not yet so we
have uh we are actually currently
working on a so this um it's actually
not so easy to implement these things in
in standard machine learning uh
toolboxes we have a so Kal is currently
looking into this uh the PHD student in
Dron um he has an implementation now and
he's now evaluating
how uh how well we can make use of this
par ization in practice but we are
actually quite confident that this
um that's for paralyzing it uh it should
be there the question is how much you
save in terms of energy because um for
these smaller scale models that we use
now reset 18 reset 15 the the effect
might be not that huge so once we ramp
this up to really larger models the
effect should be bigger but yeah this is
ongoing work
very cool thank you um and then I was
just wondering as well like this this
local error back propagation is that
something that other people have tried
with these convolution neural networks
or is this quite a new way of of
implementing it uh there is a bunch of
approaches that do this so uh there is
for example I mean the closest I guess
is Target propagation which has been
proposed which essentially uses random
feedback weights uh to back propagate
here so these these guys would not be
trained
um and those as far as I know this works
this works nicely also for small scale
um uh problems but as far as I know they
don't perform that well even for for
Cipher 10 they they it already starts
breaking down because these random
feedback weights are just too coarse an
approximation I think and this is the
first um okay maybe I have to be careful
I think this is the first um method that
allows you to train this feedback
weights that is not a contrastive method
so there's a bunch of methods that use a
contrastive step
um so you have maybe seen this forward
forward algorithm and and all these
things but what they have to do always
is they send in
[Music]
uh uh they send in the actual input data
and then they send an kind of anti-
input so an anti- input that is uh
usually generated artificially so they
do some Distortion to the input to make
it uh and then they train the they have
to use both informations locally uh to
do the update so the network has to keep
in memory uh the input and the anti
input and the the responses and this
makes um this makes this approaches a
bit harder to parallelize in this and
the nice thing here is that we derive an
uh an upper bound to this uh variational
free energy loss that can be spelled out
completely by forward propagation and
that I think is new so that is the the
new bit of of this
[Music]
very that's
awesome well yeah few few comments one
piece that kind of between the two of
your talks that was at least a new
distinction to me which was is the
difference between the neuromorphic
hardware and the neuromorphic
algorithms so it's not just about new
hardware or
wetwear though that would be great to
see it's almost like there's this
intermediate or a bridge step with using
the
algorithms on the hardware we have
today that like Sarah mentioned the
spiking neural networks which are
amenable to gpus or just using
standardized um CPU multicore scheduling
approaches you can already do
more with what we
have using the neuromorphic algorithms
so it's not just um a material science
topic but also there's a lot at the
really micro scale that we can learn
related to noise processing scheduling
and then also even at higher levels of
abstraction probably learning from
biomimicry and cognitive systems more
generally but that was like that was a
distinction for
me yeah so maybe to to add um yeah so I
think that the problem becomes really
now more pressing as these uh
neuromorphic uh devices become Al the
hardware devices become more
mature and they usually cannot really
shine on this uh on these standard
machine learning algorithms because they
are really optimized for for
gpus so you need to think a little bit
so you have to take one step back and
think again about the algorithmic side
um to to really use them to to full
capacity and we also as you have seen
that we collaborate with um Professor
Maya who is doing this Spiner chip in
Dron but there's also other approaches
and like the L chip that Sarah mentioned
from Intel and so on um and they are
really looking into this now they also
from the algorithmic
side I I find it really useful it's kind
of like a mindset or a mental framework
when I'm thinking about computers or Ai
and I this is probably because I'm a
neuroscientist but I also have to
translate it to well how does the brain
work how does the information processing
work etc in the brain and and when I
came to sort of computer science and AI
after Neuroscience I found myself
naturally translating it but I feel like
the framework is is just a really useful
way of understanding comput at the end
of the day because our brains as I said
are just these massive supercomputers
and I'm constantly reading papers on
computer science or whatever and and
then once you you can conceptualize
anything really as well how close how
neuromorphic is this and then if you
start thinking about well how how could
you tweak it so it's slightly more
neuromorphic and is that then going to
give you these gains that we get with
the brain like is it going to give you
some like extra parallel computation or
is it going to give you some Energy
Efficiency so yeah I I find it NE like
the definitions when I was looking at
the definition is I think it really
depends your rights a definition and
because it's such a a dynamic area at
the moment as well um I think it's going
to be it has been changing and it will
be changing but for me I feel like
neuromorphic is more of a frame like a
mental framework where I look at things
through
conceptualize yeah I think it's it's
also not very well defined I mean uh in
you also mentioned that that actually
artificial neuron networks are a
neuromorphic uh concept if you want and
they were
from the first day and it's actually
it's a it's a big success story right if
you look into the 90s or so when these
support Vector machines and and these
these alternative models came up but
none of them have have outlived the the
new neuromorphic approaches so uh it's
actually very nice but still there is
this communic community that thinks that
there is more features from the brain
that you need to put in to uh to get get
to the real
thing yeah so I think this is a bit of a
it's not a very well defined term
actually and I think with your research
yours is almost like the smallest level
that I've seen people look at it on I
don't know if you've seen anything else
but we're not just talking about like a
cell level of of free energy and active
inference we're actually talking about
like a cell structure and then like so
then you think well how small does it go
are we going to talk about cell
subcellular structures you know
eventually like mitochondria using free
energy in a similar way with compound
compartments and yeah so I guess
actually' be interesting to get your
thoughts David on you know you talked at
the start about how sign upses are
compartmentalized um do you different
different sort of instantiations of this
in different compartments just in within
one signups almost like are you wanting
to sort of look at that granular level
or is it is it more now taking what
you've learned from this and putting it
back into how can we sort of you know
make the AI more
efficient uh yeah we are going much more
in this direction now that we we see how
we can build this back into um AI models
um so I think the the free energy so one
has to be a bit careful when using the
free energy principle because it's such
a powerful General framework that you
can apply it to basically
[Music]
anything um and it's not necessarily you
will come up with a useful result in the
end just applying just putting this
um and we basically I mean this started
actually as a side project this was my
kind of uh coid um pandemic lockdown um
project and I was just curious about
this and um whether you can actually
solve this because I thought the signups
is maybe simple enough that you because
when you when you go into the papers um
they have at some point to go into some
approximations they do some um meanfield
usually so they go for first modes and
then you can solve these guys for more
complex even for neurons it's hard
actually if you go to the neuron or
network level it's it's hard it's it's
very involved math but for a sinus is
simple enough actually so you can
actually do this and and spell
everything out if you make the right
assumptions and um and really just
derived these things and that was kind
of an just
an kind of a game I I I went into and
then it turned out to to work quite
nicely I think in the end yeah very
um I'm not sure if you I like
mitochondria or so I'm sure you could
apply the same principles but I'm not
sure if the results you get would be any
meaningful or would would help you in
any
way well that's that's always the the
risk you you invest so much time and
then in the end you get some results and
you don't
[Music]
know that was also something that I
thought was quite interesting which was
the synapse was the agent it's really
easy think oh we'll make a agent-based
model of a neural system first off that
tends to not include Gia or non- neural
cell types but it's almost like a doubly
unquestioned assumption that the cell
would be the
agent but then it was a great transition
from the person throwing the ball over
the wall that's an action Centric
approach where you only have partial
visibility of the
consequences and then that is the exact
scenario that the synapse finds itself
in in in a different way or it could
have been set up so that a neuron is the
agent we're building maps not
territories and so then just like you
said free energy principle it's a
principle for
everything and so just making principled
statements about things
is table
stakes and then I guess my question for
you is then what does make it useful or
in your learning and tinkering around
with these models what differentiated
situations where you applied free energy
principle or active inference and you
felt like it was providing a
contribution to your research Direction
versus where you played around and it
was like well that was to
logical um I think it the free energy
principle makes sense in in a context
where you have um incomplete
information so as soon as you so for
example in the signups case right the
question we started with was um this
problem that the signups has to solve
that it has incomplete information about
the um the state in the cell
body um because it only sees this uh
kind of or that's the Assumption at
least of the model and and also what we
get from the experimentalists that they
essentially only sees this spe
propagating action potential so sees a
single binary variable about um about
the state of the of the
Soma so essentially this is a problem of
uh of incomplete uh information and also
the second ingredient that you need an
agent that you need some form of agency
I think if you apply the free energy
principle to a a system without agency
so if something is not interacting with
an environment in a closed loop
uh then it becomes really sketchy and I
think already this model is is on the
edge when it comes because
the these these models don't really have
an agency but they at least produce an
output right so you can still think of
this as an as an interaction with an
environment but some as soon as you lose
that I think then there would be simpler
models that can just give you the
same yeah
actually in the signups in the signups
case the the agency is only this uh this
adding noise actually in the model
because the signups is triggered PR
synoptically and then it it adds this it
uses its internal state to add the right
amount of
noise which is probably already the
minimal agency you could
[Music]
imagine Sarah you want to ask a question
or I can ask a
question um yeah I was more just a
comment like I think it's quite
interesting like people talk about
biology some people say it's not real
science because it's all messy and noisy
but I think your it works really
interesting because it's like you say
the synaptic noise is actually a
reporting of uncertainty so in that
Essence it's actually probably quite
accurately reporting and and the messy
World rather than the biology itself
just being all messy but that's just
what I was thinking about um yeah I
think I was curious as well like you
said this was like your lockdown project
but I'm just interested in how you sort
of came to the free energy principle how
you came across it was it something you
were quite familiar with already or or
some of your network or peers were
talking about it or did you stumble
across it in a paper um I mean I was
when I was during my PhD I was
interested in um in variational methods
and and probabilistic methods um and
then I started reading about this and so
I read a bunch of um kristance papers
and I I found this interesting and
um actually my my PhD supervisor always
um encouraged me not to not to go in
that
direction uh and then after I finished
my PhD I thought okay now I I can do
what I want I try it
out so
yeah and then I I guess do you think it
would be worthwhile like next steps for
you or for the the field actually trying
to implement this on you know maybe some
of the more analog chips that are being
built in the space like the analog
neuromorphic chips which I know you can
have like some synaptic Dynamic synapses
and and things like do you think it' be
worthwhile um trying to implement own
hard Hardware or what your thoughts on
that um I mean the triplet rule that
comes out from this first work I showed
I think that would be interesting to
implement it um it is the nice feature
is that it it should in principle be
kind of this should have this self-
stabilizing picture because it's really
mimicking the uh the Dynamics of the the
membrane of the cell membrane so if the
if the neuromorphic hardware
would
uh so if if the the model in the signups
and and the Neuron model match up very
well the model should uh give you this
nice uh self stabilizing feature so that
neurons really not go into some
epileptic States or so and you get this
for free from this model that's what we
saw in the simulations at least
but um in the simulations of course we
we had full control over this Dynamics
matching up in the right way
so um that is probably a bit more tricky
for Hardware but it's probably solvable
so it would be interesting yeah then
what you get for it is that you have
this purely event based tools right
which only use um prepost spikes which
which is
nice very cool thank you yeah Daniel if
you had a question
well that's a great principle there
which is like if you can design the
neuromorphic algorithm so that it
harnesses a material feature like the
actual leaky permeability of a membrane
or actual spatial proximity if you can
leverage a material feature analog
feature that isn't virtualized then it's
already in
adjacency into future Hardware so that's
one great point and then to s's point
about like almost biology not being a
science which um there's a famous
quotation there will never be a Newton
for a blade of grass because some people
say yeah it's a different biology is
more like history because whether you
approach this from a development or
ecology or Evolution perspective biology
is a historical science it's not like a
real science and then that reminded me
of the cross country shirt that says our
sport is your punishment
so it's like well no like that your
noise is biology's signal and that's how
it
happens my question was about this
tension
between I guess neural and computational
ways of looking at the resources
associated with computation so from the
Von noyman Paradigm we have a lot of
shared reference points CPU Cycles Ram
capacity and all these kinds of things
and like even in your
introductions you conveyed like well
this is how many CPU Cycles it's going
through or this is how many parameters
would have to be stored or something
like
that however that's
referencing another Paradigm so what do
resource
descriptors or capacity descriptors look
like when we're outside the space of
okay yeah power consumption that's
something that you can put into a box
and just use a bomb calorimeter that's
kind of like a low hanging fruit but now
okay Beyond just the sheer energy or
caloric
requirements what can we say that is
like analogous to the way that we talk
about the processor the Ram or the hard
drive on a
computer I mean I'm yeah I I'd have to
think about that one some more I do
think there was some interesting
comments in the paper on that slide I
showed that talks about um the brain and
energy there was a paper I linked to
I'll have to get the reference and let
you know what it is because QR C's gone
now um but that had some interesting
ideas I think on what you're getting out
there but I yeah I'd have to defer to
the paper
I mean how do they describe what is
being designed do they say it has this
many of this type of component and then
that might do nothing though so how do
they describe or evaluate these
different designs or
algorithms I think it's all different
depending on the use case like that's
what I've found really like the language
is is different depending on you know if
it's written by someone maybe with more
of a neuroscience background or
engineering background and then you kind
of you said that some terms they're more
interchangeable than others but I do
think the terminology is something which
needs to be looked at a lot more closely
in the space because then I think that
will help everybody working in it to be
on the same page a little bit
closer cool
well any other thoughts or questions
David first and then Sarah also I'm very
curious what direction will this series
go but first David what are any other
kind of closing comments or directions
you want to
provide um not really um I mean I would
say thanks for for having me today was
really was really a pleasure to discuss
with
you thank you David it was amazing to
have you on I think your work's
absolutely fascinating and I think it's
going to be have lots of benefits in the
future for implementation which is
always nice to see as well um yeah so
what was the question where where do I
see the series going um hopefully we can
have a new guest each month um I think
it'd be kind of cool maybe next month to
do um to have someone who's building
Hardware so like maybe someone from the
brain scales team or spica team or
something like that would be pretty cool
um but yeah really I just want to have a
space for people who are interested in
this intersection to uh meet people who
and see talks and you know Reach Out
people who are also working in the space
because um it's pretty Niche but I think
it's pretty important um actually having
said that David could you let everybody
know like if they wanted to reach out to
you what's the best way for them to do
that
[Music]
um I'm not very active on this Discord
channel so maybe email is still the best
uh to reach out to me I
guess cool do you want to give your
email
just oh I think my email should be easy
enough to find but you can also get the
email out there
short people can check the papers and
then in the active inference Institute
Discord there's the neuromorphic
Channel all right thank you David and
Sarah really cool to see morph stream
kick off its developmental trajectory
this way so till next time thank you
bye
[Music]
fine